<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

Copyright (C) 2013-2023 The Octave Project Developers

See the file COPYRIGHT.md in the top-level directory of this
distribution or <https://octave.org/copyright/>.

This file is part of Octave.

Octave is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify it
under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License, or
(at your option) any later version.

Octave is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with Octave; see the file COPYING.  If not, see
<https://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.

-->
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>org.octave.Octave.desktop</id>
  <metadata_license>FSFAP</metadata_license>
  <project_license>GPL-3.0+</project_license>
  <name>GNU Octave</name>
  <summary>Interactive programming environment for numerical computations</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="ca">Entorn de programació interactiva per a càlculs numèrics</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="de">Interaktive Programmierumgebung für numerische Berechnungen</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="es">Entorno de programación interactiva para cálculos numéricos</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="fr">Environnement de programmation interactif pour le calcul numérique</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="hu">Interaktív programozási környezet számszerű számításokhoz</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="it">Ambiente di programmazione interattivo per il calcolo numerico</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="ja">数値計算のための対話的なプログラミング環境</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="nl">Interactieve programmeeromgeving voor numerieke berekeningen</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="pt">Ambiente de programação interativo para computação numérica</summary>
  <summary xml:lang="zh">数值计算交互式编程环境</summary>
  <description>
    <p>
      GNU Octave is a high-level interpreted language, primarily intended for
      numerical computations. It provides capabilities for the numerical
      solution of linear and nonlinear problems, and for performing other
      numerical experiments. It also provides extensive graphics capabilities
      for data visualization and manipulation. Octave is normally used through
      its interactive command line interface, but it can also be used to write
      non-interactive programs. The Octave language is quite similar to
      Matlab so that most programs are easily portable.
    </p>
    <p xml:lang="de">
      GNU Octave ist eine höhere, interpretierte Programmiersprache, die
      hauptsächlich für numerische Berechnungen gedacht ist. Sie bietet
      Funktionen für die numerische Lösung linearer und nichtlinearer Probleme
      und für die Durchführung anderer numerischer Experimente. Darüber hinaus
      bietet es umfangreiche Grafikfunktionen zur Datenvisualisierung und
      -manipulation. Octave wird normalerweise mittels einer interaktiven
      Befehlszeile verwendet, kann aber auch zum Schreiben nicht interaktiver
      Programme verwendet werden. Die Octave-Programmiersprache ist sehr
      ähnlich zu Matlab, so dass die meisten Programme leicht übertragbar sind.
    </p>
    <p xml:lang="es">
      GNU Octave es un lenguaje interpretado de alto nivel, destinado
      principalmente a cálculos numéricos. Dispone capacidades para
      la solución numérica de problemas lineales y no lineales, y para
      realizar otros experimentos numéricos. También proporciona amplias
      funcionalidades gráficas para la visualización y manipulación de datos.
      Octave se usa normalmente a través de su interfaz de línea de comandos
      interactiva, pero también se puede usar para escribir programas no
      interactivos. El lenguaje Octave es muy similar a Matlab,
      por lo que la mayoría de los programas son fáciles de portar.
    </p>
    <p xml:lang="fr">
      GNU Octave est un langage de programmation interprété, destiné
      principalement au calcul numérique. Il fournit des fonctionnalités
      pour la résolution de problèmes linéaires et non-linéaires, et pour toutes
      sortes d'expériences numériques.  Il s'accompagne d'un système complet
      de visualisation et de manipulation des données. Octave s’utilise
      généralement via son environnement en lignes de commandes interactif,
      mais il peut aussi être utilisé pour écrire des programmes non
      interactifs. Le langage Octave est très similaire à Matlab de telle sorte
      que les programmes Matlab sont très faciles à porter sous Octave.
    </p>
    <p xml:lang="hu">
      A GNU Octave egy magas szintű értelmezett nyelv, elsősorban numerikus
      számításokhoz. Képességeket biztosít a lineáris és nemlineáris problémák
      numerikus megoldására, valamint egyéb numerikus kísérletek elvégzésére.
      Ezenkívül kiterjedt grafikus képességeket biztosít az adatok
      megjelenítéséhez és manipulálásához. Az Octave-t általában az interaktív
      parancssori felületen keresztül használják, de nem interaktív programok
      írására is használható. Az Octave nyelv nagyon hasonló a Matlabhoz, így
      a legtöbb program könnyen hordozható.
    </p>
    <p xml:lang="nl">
      GNU Octave is een hogere geïnterpreteerde taal, primair bedoeld voor
      numerieke berekeningen. Het biedt mogelijkheden voor het numeriek
      oplossen van lineaire en niet-lineaire problemen en andere numerieke
      experimenten. Ook biedt het uitgebreide mogelijkheden for grafische
      visualisatie en -manipulatie van data. Octave wordt meestal gebruikt
      door middel van zijn interactieve opdrachtregelinterface (terminal)
      maar kan ook gebruikt worden voor het schrijven van niet-interactieve
      programma's. Octave's taal lijkt zeer veel op die van Matlab zodat de
      meeste Matlabcode simpel te draaien is in Octave.
    </p>
    <p>
      Octave has extensive tools for solving common numerical linear algebra
      problems, finding the roots of nonlinear equations, integrating ordinary
      functions, manipulating polynomials, and integrating ordinary
      differential and differential-algebraic equations. It is easily
      extensible and customizable via user-defined functions written in
      Octave's own language, or using dynamically loaded modules written in
      C++, C, Fortran, or other languages.
    </p>
    <p xml:lang="de">
      Octave verfügt über umfangreiche Werkzeuge zur Lösung gängiger
      numerischer linearer Probleme der Algebra, zum Auffinden der Nullstellen
      nichtlinearer Gleichungen, zur Integration gewöhnlicher Funktionen, zur
      Manipulation von Polynomen und zur Integration gewöhnlicher
      Differentialgleichungen und differential-algebraischer Gleichungen. Es
      ist leicht erweiter- und anpassbar mittels benutzerdefinierter
      Funktionen, die in Octaves eigener Programmiersprache geschrieben wurden,
      oder über dynamisch geladene, in C++, C, Fortran oder anderen Sprachen
      geschriebene Module.
    </p>
    <p xml:lang="es">
      Octave dispone de una amplia variedad de herramientas para resolver
      problemas comunes de álgebra lineal numérica, encontrar
      las raíces de ecuaciones no lineales, integrar funciones ordinarias,
      manipular polinomios e integrar ecuaciones diferenciales ordinarias
      y algebraicas diferenciales. Es fácilmente extensible y personalizable
      a través de funciones definidas por el usuario escritas en el propio
      lenguaje de Octave, o utilizando módulos cargados dinámicamente
      escritos en C ++, C, Fortran u otros idiomas.
    </p>
    <p xml:lang="fr">
      Octave dispose de nombreux outils pour résoudre les problèmes classiques
      d'algèbre linéaire, trouver les racines d'équations non-linéaires,
      intégrer les fonctions ordinaires et les équations différentielles.
      Il peut très facilement être étendu en définissant de nouvelles
      fonctions écrites en langage Octave ou en utilisant des modules
      chargés dynamiquement, écrits en C++, C, Fortran ou autres langages.
    </p>
    <p xml:lang="hu">
      Az Octave kiterjedt eszközökkel rendelkezik a gyakori numerikus lineáris
      algebrai problémák megoldásához, a nemlineáris egyenletek gyökereinek
      megkereséséhez, a hétköznapi függvények integrálásához, a polinomok
      manipulálásához, valamint a közönséges differenciál- és differenciál-
      algebrai egyenletek integrálásához. Könnyen bővíthető és testreszabható
      a felhasználó által meghatározott, Octave saját nyelvén írt funkciókkal,
      vagy dinamikusan betöltött modulokkal, C++, C, Fortran vagy más
      nyelveken.
    </p>
    <p xml:lang="nl">
      Octave heeft een uitgebreide verzameling gereedschappen for het oplossen
      van numerieke lineaire-algebra vraagstukken, vinden van wortels van
      niet-lineaire vergelijkingen, integreren van gewone functies, manipuleren
      van polynomen en integreren van gewone differentiaal- en algebrïsche
      differentiaalvergelijkingen. Het is makkelijk uit te breiden en aan te
      passen met behulp van door zelfgemaakte functies geschreven in Octave's
      eigen taal en/of met dynamische te laden modules gechreven in C++, C,
      Fortran of andere programmeertalen.
    </p>
  </description>

  <screenshots>
    <!--
      From: https://www.freedesktop.org/software/appstream/docs/
      All screenshots should have a 16:9 aspect ratio, and should have
      a width that is no smaller than 620px. Screenshots should be in PNG
      or JPEG format. PNG is the preferred format.
    -->
    <screenshot type="default">
      <image>https://www.gnu.org/software/octave/img/screenshot.png</image>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>

  <launchable type="desktop-id">org.octave.Octave.desktop</launchable>
  <provides>
    <binary>octave</binary>
  </provides>

  <url type="homepage">https://www.octave.org/</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://bugs.octave.org/</url>
  <url type="donation">https://www.octave.org/donate.html</url>
  <url type="faq">https://wiki.octave.org/FAQ</url>
  <update_contact>maintainers@octave.org</update_contact>
  <project_group>GNU</project_group>
  <developer_name>John W. Eaton and others</developer_name>
  <content_rating type="oars-1.0"/>
  <releases>
    <release date="2023-04-13" version="8.2.0"/>
    <release date="2023-03-07" version="8.1.0"/>
    <release date="2022-11-02" version="7.3.0"/>
    <release date="2022-07-28" version="7.2.0"/>
    <release date="2022-04-06" version="7.1.0"/>
    <release date="2021-10-30" version="6.4.0"/>
    <release date="2021-07-11" version="6.3.0"/>
    <release date="2021-02-19" version="6.2.0"/>
    <release date="2020-11-26" version="6.1.0"/>
    <release date="2020-01-31" version="5.2.0"/>
    <release date="2019-02-23" version="5.1.0"/>
    <release date="2018-08-09" version="4.4.1"/>
    <release date="2018-04-30" version="4.4.0"/>
    <release date="2018-03-13" version="4.2.2"/>
  </releases>
</component>
